<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>a r a</title>
    <description>A blog by Allison Atwill</description>
    <link>http://allisonatwill.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://allisonatwill.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2015 20:03:32 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2015 20:03:32 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>10x the energy at 2x the cost</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;section heading&quot;&gt;The human body, man. How does it work? &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am obsessed with life optimization.  Every day we make hundreds of small decisions that have profound effects on our mental and physical state.  I want to get the most out of my time every day, so I run lots of experiments to maximize my energy and mental productivity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important thing you can do to increase your energy levels is to understand that your body works as an energetic system. While plants get their energy from the sun and the dirt, us animals get our energy from the food we put in our mouths.  All of your great ideas first started out as food!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To maximize the energy available to your brain, you can optimize three basic systems: 1. Facilitate the flow of available nutrition around your body. 2. Increase the quantity of nutrition in your body through food choice. 3. Increase your body’s ability to process nutrition from food. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section heading&quot;&gt;Blood: The basic pathway &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blood is the way water-soluble vitamins, minerals, amino acids, and electrolytes get where they need to go in our bodies.  This system has a pump, which is our big beautiful heart, and the better our heart works, the better this system performs.  The way to optimize blood flow is pretty simple. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Don’t skip leg day.  But after that: &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Don’t skip cardio day. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section heading&quot;&gt;Lymph: It&#39;s a thing &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesser-known circulatory pathway is the lymphatic system. Lymphatic fluid is the body’s waterway, and it’s how fat-soluble minerals and vitamins like A, D, E, and K travel though our bodies. It’s also how lymphocytes, the disease fighting white blood cells, get around.  Unlike blood, lymphatic fluid has no pump to move it around.  Instead, we have to move it ourselves!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever taken a yoga class, you probably felt pretty amazing afterwards.  The teacher may also have talked about “moving energy” through the body.  It’s not just a new agey idea, it’s actually a very real physical process.  By bending and stretching, we move old interstitial fluid away from our tissues and help vitamins and white blood cells reach their intended bodily destination.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get the most out of your lymph, there are two main methods of optimization: drink a lot of water, and stretch your body out.   Drink the most distilled water you can find.  Protip: get a reverse-osmosis water filter, which takes out the disinfectants that are used to treat tap water.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; I’ve also taken to “urban lifestyle yoga,” which is doing yoga stretches whenever you feel like it out in the wild.  You may get some strange looks, but little do those people know how great you feel from an efficient movement of lymphatic fluid! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/yoga-sequence.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Art School wasn&#39;t really in the cards for me&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;I bet your lymphatic system would feel pretty good if you did this sequence right now!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section heading&quot;&gt;Micronutrition: Lego blocks of immune response &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second way to increase your available energy resources is to maximize the total volume of nutrition flowing around.  Below calories and the macronutrients are micronutrients. Vitamins and minerals. These are the building blocks of new tissue.  Good micronutrition is like having a giant bucket of legos. Your body can build anything that it wants! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To maximize micronutrition, the best thing you can do is to eat plants. Fruits and vegetables. We are still 100% animals and not yet cyborgs, so plant food is where micronutrition is most bio-available to us.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As anyone else who has tried to hack their body by eating only protein bars and multivitamins will know, taking a supplement is not the same as eating food.  The nutrition in supplement-based food like Soylent is not only less bioavailable, it’s also missing a crucial element.  We don’t just need the building blocks of micronutrition, we also need the processing agents--bacteria. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/farmers-market.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nom&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Nom&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section heading&quot;&gt;The microbiome: We are not alone &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If vitamins and minerals are micronutrition, then bacteria is nanonutrition.  The human body is comprised of 10x more bacterial cells than human cells.  Don’t freak out, but you and I are living with almost 3 pounds of bacterial symbiotes inside of us, and they are known as the microbiome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The microbiome is responsible for nutrient processing and energy extraction from the small intestine into the circulatory system.  It is where some of the best neurotransmitters like dopamine and serotonin are created. A damaged microbiome results in depression, lowered immune response, and chronic health conditions like celiac and leaky gut syndrome.  A healthy microbiome means that you can extract maximal energy out of the food you eat! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section heading&quot;&gt;Kombucha = life. Literally. &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bacteria in our microbiome are damaged by most pesticides.  Pesticides are designed to kill bacteria!   Glyphosate, the active ingredient in Roundup, is the most widely used herbicide in American farming. It&#39;s also patented as an antibiotic. That&#39;s not good for our  microbes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-organic food decreases your energy levels over time by killing your digestive bacteria. Organic food adds to your energy levels by feeding your microbiome, which is then able to extract more energy for you to use. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t ready to dedicate yourself full-force to eating only organic, you can still hack this system.  Probiotic foods like yogurt, sauerkraut, and especially kombucha are all full of bacterial nanonutrition that replenish your microbiome.  Kombucha especially because it’s the tastiest :) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try eating organic and drinking kombucha every day for a week, and tell me that you don’t feel absolutely amazing. For the price sensitive: It’s widely accepted that the path to material wealth is to invest money where it will generate the highest return on investment.  Investing in your food is the single best decision you can make for your brain, your happiness,  and your life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section heading&quot;&gt;TL;DR Action Plan &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Food is our energy source. Blood and lymph are how energy gets around the body.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lymph only moves when we move it.  Drink water and do some yoga stretches to get that lymph cruising around your body.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Micronutrition is what makes our bodies healthy.  It’s not effective to get it from supplements. Eat fruits and vegetables.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bacteria are our friends!  Your microbiome is the processing plant for food energy. Pesticides kill the microbiome. Don’t kill your microbiome, feed your microbiome!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eat organic food. Drink kombucha. Feel amazing.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/kombucha-bow.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pairing photographed for artistic effect&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Kombucha AND yoga. Two of my favorite things!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section heading&quot;&gt;Thanks! &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there you have it!  This has been a fascinating topic for me to research, because it helped me become more dispassionate towards the role of food and exercise in my life.  I started viewing my body as a system to be optimized, and began paying attention to the feedback loop of food inputs and productivity outputs.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I understood the cycle, my daily decisions were weighed against a much more simple equation.  If it brings you energy, do it!  If it takes it away, don’t :) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; I hope you found this informative and useful as well! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;section heading&quot;&gt; Resources for the curious: &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do some living room yoga!  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Is8tMCpv4F8&quot;&gt;YouTube is full of classes, no gym needed.&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK154098&quot;&gt;The Human Microbiome, Diet, and Health: Workshop Summary.&lt;/a&gt; Institute of Medicine (US) Food Forum. 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/patents/US7771736&quot;&gt; Glyphosate formulations and their use for the inhibition of 5-enolpyruvylshikimate-3-phosphate synthase. &lt;/a&gt; US Patent US7771736 B2. [Glyphosate as an antibiotic]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19105591&quot;&gt;Glyphosate formulations induce apoptosis and necrosis in human umbilical, embryonic, and placental cells. &lt;/a&gt;Benachour N, Séralini GE. Chem Res Toxicol. 2009. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22200534&quot;&gt; A glyphosate-based herbicide induces necrosis and apoptosis in mature rat testicular cells in vitro, and testosterone decrease at lower levels.  &lt;/a&gt; Clair E, Mesnage R, Travert C, Séralini GÉ. Toxicol In Vitro. 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.who.int/ipcs/features/hazardous_pesticides.pdf&quot;&gt;Exposure to highly hazardous pesticides: a major public health concern.&lt;/a&gt; World Health Organization. 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2015 04:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://allisonatwill.github.io/2015/11/16/organic-kombucha-microbiome/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://allisonatwill.github.io/2015/11/16/organic-kombucha-microbiome/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Linear Programming for your Lifestyle</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Understanding and prioritizing your fundamental resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As trade-off talking rational economic people, we are constantly making choices that have different costs associated with them. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three main metrics of resource expenditure against which I evaluate the cost of my decisions are, in rough order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Financial resources&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Time resources &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Physical resources (bodily and emotional fatigue)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of individual choice analysis can also be expressed as a simple optimization problem, as described by this reward function: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/utility-function.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Simple Utility&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Where F = financial resources and W&lt;sub&gt;f&lt;/sub&gt; = Weight of financial resources (how much I care about preserving them).  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a loosely formulized way of looking at the age-old discipline of budgeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; The application of these principles has allowed me to maximize my utility within my resource constraints. Not being an engineer by trade and working outside of the technology sector, my monetary compensation is lower than many of my peers. When I personally solve for this equation, W&lt;sub&gt;f&lt;/sub&gt; is weighted higher than W&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt; and W&lt;sub&gt;p&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Constructing your budget framework&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a budget conscious person out of necessity.  Left to their own devices, my material desires would scale infinitely upwards. If I had the appropriate wealth and income level, I&#39;d undoubetdly be building my own personal spaceship right next to Elon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, my profitable years have thus far yielded only a linear increase in my spending power. It is therefore necessary to  realistically constrain this aspect of my life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; I structure my budget with a traditional 33% split: after maxing out employer-matched 401k contributions, take-home income should be divided evenly between housing, savings, and spending. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/dragonv2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Elon&#39;s Dream&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;One day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Why we save&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Unfortunately, life is rarely so elegantly divided.  Within a budget framework, each expense must have it’s own weight. Here, I take Warren Buffett’s advice, which gives saving a strong priority over spending. This is because, simply put, saving money helps you maximize your long-term utility&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saving in the present means that in the future, it is possible to make larger investments in securities, businesses, or property that will generate passive income. This is key to long-term wealth creation, and so in my own budget framework I weight saving more strongly than spending.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/lake-garda.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lake Garda&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Of course, we also save just so we can spend more later. I got to go on some great trips this year.  This is Lake Garda, in Northern Italy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Housing in America&#39;s hottest market&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt; I live in San Francisco, where the median rent for new one and two bedroom apartments in the city is now the highest in the United States.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;   These rent prices are driven primarily by constrained housing supply, coupled with rapid job creation in the technology sector where median wages are high. Not working directly in the technology sector, I have to adjust my budget framework to account for these trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Searching for an apartment was an exercise in short- vs. long-term resource tradeoffs. I invested a significant amount of time and energy hunting down an apartment.  I wanted to maximize apartment quality while constrained in the following areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
 	&lt;li&gt;Income&lt;/li&gt; 
 	&lt;li&gt;Geographic location&lt;/li&gt;
 	&lt;li&gt;Aesthetic preferences&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, I first had to understand the market.  I evaluated every Craigslist apartment listing in our search radius every single day for 3 months. I also checked Trulia, Zillow, RentSFNow, and canvassed our preferred neighborhoods writing down phone numbers of the &quot;Apartment Available&quot; signs.  As a tip, Craigslist is by far the most useful and comprehensive source for apartment rentals in San Francisco. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the apartments I researched, I visited ~15 units, and applied with my wonderful roommate to 3 of those units before signing our current lease.  By expending my short term time and physical resources, we now have a beautiful apartment that, by my estimation, is priced significantly below market while being in a maximally ideal location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/sharonodegaard-filbert.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Filbert Steps&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;The ideal daily commute.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;The role of housing in the reward function&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Including the variable cost of utilities, I currently spend ~37% of my income on housing, +4% to the ideal budget split.  Given my preference for saving over spending, I make this up by constraining my other expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an acceptable tradeoff to me for several reasons. Most importantly, my apartment’s location allows me to gain in other resources some of what I trade financially. My daily commute to work is a 6 minute walk down the Filbert Steps. My apartment is also in an exceptionally beautiful part of San Francisco, which is emotionally beneficial to me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; If we’re looking at this in the optimization framework I proposed earlier, I’m now spending more of my financial resources to gain time and physical resources, which nets me greater utility overall.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/housing-utility-function.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The equation at work&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Understanding your maximum spend, and optimizing within it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt; After factoring in a 33% savings rate and ~37% housing expense, this leaves me ~30% of my income to spend in a given month.  Of this, my three main variable expense categories are food, clothing, and entertainment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entertainment costs are difficult to hack, because they are so much determined by social group dynamics. Concert ticket prices generally have a lower bound, as do dinners out.  Budgeting most social activities therefore becomes a simple matter of inclusion or exclusion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve personally found the most opportunity for optimization in what I spend on food and clothing. I have strong preferences for premium quality products in both of these areas, which necessitates some creative purchasing when operating within a constrained budget. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/img/mushroom.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Living off the land.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Though stringent, my budgeting has not yet led me to scavenging for food. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Applying the framework&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned, my resource constraints are atypical for this area.  Individuals working at technology jobs in the South Bay are usually awarded higher wages to compensate for significant time lost in multi-hour daily commutes. Engineers are also compensated at higher rates to account for the scarcity of their skills and the larger number of productive hours required in programming roles.  In these cases, a personal budget framework would focus more on time optimization, while being less constrained by financial resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In it’s practical application, operating within a budget requires constant renegotiation between preferences, available resources, and constraints. Each person has unique available resource levels and varying preferences given to the tradeoffs that they make in their lives. This is a logical model that I have found useful in analyzing my own economic tradeoffs, and optimizing within my own economic reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Trade-off_talking_rational_economic_person&quot;&gt;Trade-off talking rational economic person. (2013, May 22). In Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.warrenbuffett.com/warren-buffett-10-ways-to-get-rich/&quot;&gt; Warren Buffett’s 10 Ways to Get Rich&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.zumper.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/January-2015-Rent-Report.pdf&quot;&gt;January 2015 Rent Report by Zumper&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2015 04:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://allisonatwill.github.io/2015/02/08/resource-constrained-budget-optimization/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://allisonatwill.github.io/2015/02/08/resource-constrained-budget-optimization/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
