<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>a r a</title>
    <description>An elegant blog using the Clean Blog template</description>
    <link>http://allisonatwill.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://allisonatwill.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2015 23:15:17 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2015 23:15:17 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Understand Your Budget, Hack Your Life</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Understanding and prioritizing your fundamental resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As trade-off talking rational economic people, we are constantly making choices that have different costs associated with them. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three main metrics of resource expenditure against which I evaluate the cost of my decisions are, in rough order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Financial resources&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Time resources &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Physical resources (bodily and emotional fatigue)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post will focus on optimizing your life within constrained financial resources, otherwise known as budgeting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Constructing your budget framework&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a budget conscious person out of necessity.  Left to their own devices, my material desires would scale infinitely upwards. If I had the appropriate wealth and income level, I would be building my own personal spaceship right next to Elon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, my profitable years have thus far yielded only a linear increase in my spending power. It is therefore necessary to  realistically constrain this aspect of my life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; I attempt to follow the traditional 33% split: after maxing out employer-matched 401k contributions, take-home income should be divided evenly between housing, savings, and spending. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/img/dragonv2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Elon&#39;s Dream&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;I want one.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Why we save&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt; I follow Warren Buffett’s strategy for personal finance, which gives saving a strong priority over spending. Saving money is important for myriad reasons, but, simply put, saving money gives you the freedom of the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending more money than you earn is obviously unsustainable, but it is also an inefficient use of future resources.  For example, not paying off a credit card bill in full results in owing additional interest on that debt, and is therefore constrains future resources needlessly.  The benefits of saving are similarly significant.  There is very real utility in the peace of mind that comes with having liquid assets that cover 6 months of personal expenses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, saving in the present means that in the future, it becomes possible to make larger investments in businesses or property that will generate passive income. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/img/lake-garda.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lake Garda&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Of course, we also save so we can spend more later. I got to go on some great trips this year.  This is Lake Garda, in Northern Italy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Housing in America&#39;s hottest market&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt; I live in San Francisco, where the median rent for new one and two bedroom apartments in the city is now the highest in the Untied States. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;   These rent prices are driven primarily by constrained housing supply, coupled with rapid job creation in the technology sector where median wages are high. Not working directly in the technology sector, I have to adjust my budget framework to account for these trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Including the variable cost of utilities, I currently spend ~37% of my income on housing, +4% to the ideal budget split.  Given my preference for saving over spending, I make this up by constaining my other expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an acceptable tradeoff to me for several reasons.  Most importantly, my apartment’s location allows me to make up in time some of what I trade financially.  My commute to work is a 6 minute walk down the Filbert Steps. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Searching for an apartment was also an exercise in short- vs. long-term resource tradeoffs. I invested a significant amount of time and energy hunting down an apartment.  I wanted to maximize apartment quality while constrained in the following areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
 	&lt;li&gt;Budget &lt;/li&gt; 
 	&lt;li&gt;Geographic location&lt;/li&gt;
 	&lt;li&gt;Aesthetic preferences&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, I first had to understand the market.  I evaluated every Criagslist apartment listing in our search radius every single day for 3 months. I also checked Trulia, Zillow, RentSFNow, and canvassed our preferred neighborhoods writing down phone numbers of the &quot;Apartment Available&quot; signs.  As a tip, Craigslist is by far the most useful and comprehensive source for apartment rentals in San Francisco. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the apartments I researched, I visited ~15 units, and applied with my roommate to 3 of those units before signing our current lease.  By expending my short term time and physical resources, we now have a beautiful apartment that, by my estimation, is significantly below market while being in a maximally ideal location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/sharonodegaard-filbert.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Filbert Steps&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Is it still a commute if you enjoy it every time?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Understanding your maximum spend, and optimizing within it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt; After factoring in a 33% savings rate and ~37% housing expense, this leaves me ~30% of my income to spend in a given month.  Of this, my three main variable expense categories are food, clothing, and entertainment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entertainment costs are difficult to hack, because they are so much determined by social group dynamics. Concert ticket prices, for example, generally have a lower bound, as do dinners out.  Budgeting most social activities therefore becomes a simple matter of inclusion or exclusion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve personally found the most opportunity for optimization in what I spend on food and clothing. I have strong preferences for premium quality products in both of these areas, which necessitates some creative purchasing when operating with a constrained budget. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/img/mushroom.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Living off the land.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Though stringent, my budgeting has not yet led me to scavenging for food. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Applying the framework&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that my resource constraints are atypical for this area.  For example, those working at technology jobs in the South Bay are usually awarded higher wages to compensate for significant time lost in a multi-hour daily commute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those individuals, a personal budget framework would focus more on time optimization, while being less constrained by financial resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Budgeting is the constant renegotiation between preferences, available resources, and constraints.  Each person has unique situational constraints and varying preferences given to the resource tradeoffs that they make in their lives.  This is a logical model that I have found helpful in analyzing my own personal economic tradeoffs, and optimizing within my unique economic reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Trade-off talking rational economic person. (2013, May 22). In Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia. Retrieved from http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Trade-off_talking_rational_economic_person &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;http://www.warrenbuffett.com/warren-buffett-10-ways-to-get-rich/ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;http://blog.zumper.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/January-2015-Rent-Report.pdf &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2015 04:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://allisonatwill.github.io/2015/02/06/resource-constrained-budget-optimization/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://allisonatwill.github.io/2015/02/06/resource-constrained-budget-optimization/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
